Preliminary Guide to the Patricia Rowe Willrich Papers, 1949-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Patricia Rowe Willrich papers 1949-1996
Willrich, Patrica Rowe
2.25 linear feet Extent: 750 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01394
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library recieved the collection as a gift from Mason Willrich in 1998.
Biographical Note
Particia Rowe Willrich was a free-lance writer, speaker, and teacher who made presentations about selected contemporary American authors at bookstores, libraries, clubs, senior centers, etc.
Collection Overview
The Patricia Rowe Willrich Papers, 1948-1996, are comprised of published and unpublished autobiographical writings; essays and lectures on contemporary American authors; correspondence with contemporary American authors; and miscellaneous other papers related to 20th century American literature. The writers featured in the correspondence include Maxine Hong Kingston, Larry McMurtry, John McPhee, Reynolds Price, Wallace Stegner, Peter Taylor, and Anne Tyler. The most extensive correspondence is with Anne Tyler and is arranged in the Anne Tyler Papers Series.
Subject Headings
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; American Literature -- 20th century -- Criticism; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Interviews; Patricia Rowe Willrich; Maxine Hong Kingston -- Correspondence; Larry McMurtry -- Correspondence; John McPhee -- Correspondence; Reynolds Price -- Correspondence; Wallace Stegner -- Correspondence; Peter Taylor -- Correspondence; Anne Tyler -- Correspondence
Detailed Description of Collection: Accession 1998-0465
- Writings and Speeches
  Typscripts of college essays, short stories, autobiographical sketches, and essays on contemporary American authors.
  - Early Writings, ca. 1948-1949, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence with Seventeen magazine concerning stories submitted for publication.
  - College Writings,1960 (Box 1)
  - Creative Writing, 1979-1991, undated, (9 folders) (Box 1)
    Autobiographical writings and short stories, chiefly written for creative writing classes.
  - Poetry, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Essays on Contemporary Authors
    Essays and lectures written by Willrich for presentations on contemporary American authors at bookstores, libraries, clubs, senior centers, etc. Arranged alphabetically by author or subject.
    - Anne Beattie, undated (Box 1)
    - Saul Bellow - first draft, undated (Box 1)
    - Truman Capote, 1983-1993, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - Raymond Carver, 1990 (Box 1)
    - John Cheever, undated (Box 1)
    - Anne Dillard, undated (Box 1)
    - E.L. Doctorow, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Louise Erdrich, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Richard Ford, undated (Box 1)
    - Ellen Gilchrist, undated (Box 1)
    - Gail Godwin, undated (Box 1)
    - Kazuo Ishiguro, undated (Box 1)
    - William Kennedy (Box 1)
    - Maxine Hong Kingston, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Anne Morrow Lindbergh (Box 1)
    - Bobbi Anne Mason (Box 1)
    - Cormac McCarthy, undated (Box 1)
    - Larry McMurtry, 1987, 1990, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Toni Morrison, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Joyce Carol Oates, undated (Box 1)
    - Reynolds Price, undated (Box 1)
    - Southern Literature, 1992 (Box 1)
    - San Francisco Literary History (Box 1)
    - Stanford Writing Program, undated (Box 1)
    - Wallace Stegner, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Gertrude Stein, undated (Box 1)
    - William Styron, undated (Box 1)
    - Peter Taylor, undated (Box 1)
    - Anne Tyler, undated (Box 1)
    - John Updike, undated (Box 1)
    - Alice Walker, undated (Box 1)
    - Eudora Welty, undated (Box 1)
  - "Patricia Rowe Willrich: Literary Works, Vol. I-III" (Box 1)
    Duplicates of some of Willrich's writings and correspondence. Volume I: Essays on American Fiction Writers; Vol. II: Correspondence with American Authors; Volume III: Autobiographical and Creative Writings, Professional Notes.
- Correspondence1980s-1990s
  Willrich's correspondence with American authors. Some correspondence files include transcripts of interviews, notes, clippings, and other related materials. Files are arranged alphabetically by author. For Anne Tyler's correspondence see the Anne Tyler Papers Series.
  - Roger Angell (Box 2)
  - Anne Beattie (Box 2)
  - Peter Benchley (Box 2)
  - Carolyn Cassady (Box 2)
  - Alan Cheuse (Box 2)
  - Robert Croft (Box 2)
  - Gail Goodwin (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth Hardwick (Box 2)
  - William Kennedy (Box 2)
  - Maxine Hong Kingston (Box 2)
  - John L'Heureux (Box 2)
  - Ann McLaughlin (Box 2)
  - Larry McMurtry (Box 2)
  - John McPhee (Box 2)
  - Joyce Carol Oates (Box 2)
  - Reynolds Price (Box 2)
    Includes cassette tape and transcript of a1990interview with Reynolds Price.
  - Nesta Ramazani (Box 2)
  - Wallace Stegner (Box 2)
    Includes photographs of Stegner and correspondence with others concerning Stegner's death.
  - Elizabeth Tallent (Box 2)
  - Peter Taylor (Box 2)
  - Alice Walker (Box 2)
  - Eudora Welty (Box 2)
  - Alan Williams (Box 2)
    Williams is an editor at Viking Press. Includes correspondence with and concerning Arturo Islas.
- Anne Tyler Papers
  Chiefly correspondence between Willrich and Anne Tyler, 1983-1996.Includes some writings about Tyler's work and notes and recollections of meetings with Tyler. Topics of letters include family issues, travel, and writing. In several letters Tyler responds in depth to Willrich's questions about her life and work.
  - Correspondence, 1983-1996, (13 folders) (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1986-1996, (10 folders) (Box 3)
    Notes written by Willrich after meeting Anne Tyler for lunch on several occasions between 1986-1993;notes from letters and articles about Tyler.
- Miscellaneous
  - Clippings (Box 3)
  - Kepler's Bookstore Bookgroup, Fall1994 (Box 3)
  - Suggested Summer Reading Lists (Box 3)
  - Promotional Materials (Box 3)
  - Course Fliers (Box 3)
  - Pen/Faulkner Materials,1989 (Box 3)
  - Book Proposal (Box 3)